<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands bane: or, The description of drunkennesse. Composed and written by Thomas Young, sometimes student of Staple-Inne</title>
            <author>Young, Thomas, student of Staple Inn.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15850</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26116</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120602</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855797</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855797</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21300</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15850)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21300)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1018:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands bane: or, The description of drunkennesse. Composed and written by Thomas Young, sometimes student of Staple-Inne</title>
                  <author>Young, Thomas, student of Staple Inn.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Iones, and are to be sold by Thomas Baylee, at the corner shop in the middle rowe in Holborne, neere adioyning vnto Staple Inne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>Variant: imprint has "Bayle".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Title page, A2-3 cropped at head.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alcoholism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21300:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21300:1"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS BANE: <hi>OR,</hi> THE DESCRIPTION <hi>of Drunkenneſſe.</hi> COMPOSED AND WRITTEN by THOMAS YOVNG, ſometimes Student of STAPLE-INNE.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Preſtat non naſei, quam male viuere.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLES: 8.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Becauſe ſentence againſt an euill worke is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the heart of the children of men is fully ſet in them to doe euill.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM IONES, and are to be ſold by THOMAS BAYLEE, at the corner ſhop in the middle rowe in <hi>Holborne,</hi> neere adioyning vnto <hi>Staple Inne.</hi> 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21300:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21300:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL VERY WORTHY indicious and vnderſtanding Gentleman Sr. FRANCIS DOWSE <hi>Knight,</hi> T. Y. <hi>wiſheth</hi> encreaſe of health and perpetuall <hi>happineſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhipfull, calling to minde my owne follies (euer from mine Infancy, prone to haue coniunction with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancie the chiefe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all mens perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and alſo remembring your good counſell euer giuen vnto me, that I ſhould loath exceſſe, &amp; loue temperance (which I now finde of it ſelfe to be the treaſure of vertue,) compelling men to follow Reaſon, bringing peace to the minde, and mollifying the affections with concord and agreement, receiuing I ſay from you, not onely good aduice (being as great a benefit as one friend can doe to another) but alſo good example which is the readyeſt path-way to guide men to felicitie, and for feare I ſhould bee culpable according to the prouerbe; Thankes waxeth old as ſoone as gifts are had in poſseſsion I thought good although I cannot requite, yet to make knowne to your Worſhip, that I do not forget (for <hi>omnium in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiſsimus
<pb facs="tcp:21300:3"/>eſt,
<note place="margin">Ingratus qui be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficium accepiſſe negat, quod acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit: Ingratus qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d diſſimulat, vurſum Ingratus qui non reddit: et omnium In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiſſimus qui oblitus eſt.</note> qui oblitus eſt:</hi> neither this: nor other your manifold great &amp; continuall kindnes beſtowed vpon me: And that you may ſee how good a ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler I haue proued in the arte of ſobrietie by your diſcipline conſiliatorie and exemplarie. I am im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened to craue your patronage to this pamphlet which will at large ſet downe all the ſubtle ſleights, tempting baites, and craftie allurements, which Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan vſeth for the ouerthrow of mankinde, by this vice of drunkennes, (which indeede is the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litane citie of all the prouince of vices) which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon made me intitle my Booke, <hi>Englands Bane:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no Nation is more polluted with this capitoll ſinne, then ours. And I proteſt it is not ambition that made me craue the patronage to this Treatiſe: (conſidering my ſmall deſeruings) but chiefely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming vpon the affiance of your good nature and kinde conſtructions of my weake endeauours, and ſomething the rather, becauſe I know your liberall qualities inclinable to the Rule of my intentions: which is not to barre Societie, but to condemne Ebrietie;
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 31.23. Pro. 22.9.</note> For <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that is liberall ſhall bee bleſt, and honoured of his neighbours:</hi> And of this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, I know both your ſelfe and all your Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Family: fully indued; for often haue I heard you ſay, that of the Wine and Beere you regarded not the expence: but you blamed ſuch as would abuſe theſe creatures to ouerthrowe their owne ſence, and ſuch voluptuous liuers are them I chiefely ayme at, that cannot take moderation to bee their guide: <hi>Omne nocet nimium, mediocriter omne geren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,</hi> I know you loue to Reade: becauſe you
<pb facs="tcp:21300:3"/>know to cenſure? Let mee therefore intreat your Worſhip to reade this, and to giue it fauourable protection to the world: although the lines be rude, the matters good, and it is no ſhame to gather a Primroſe growing among Briers, had it better you ſhould enioy it, ſuch as it is if you entertaine I ſhall reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips in all faithfull obſeruance,</hi> THO: YOVNG.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21300:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21300:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>ONG</hi> I am I confeſſe who take vpon mee to correct an enormitie crept into my country, too much frequented by yong and old of all conditions. Yet (gentle Reader) let me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thee to peruſe the ſame, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different eye: not contemning any part thereof, becauſe it is compiled by the Yong. And although thou mayeſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps iuſtly ſay, that I haue beene equall with thee in this aſperſion, yet let mee entreat againe that thou wilt no leſſe equall me in my contrition) then reſolue fully to concurre with me in my conuerſion. Our Nation hath had for many yeeres ſince this imputation, that we ſhould ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like imitate Forraigne countries in their vices, wherein I will not particularize for auoiding of offence, and the rather becauſe it is to all iudiciall men too perſpicuous, I could rather wiſh that leauing their examples in the worſt, we did frame our ſelues to imitate, to compare, nay to excell them in their vertues and heroicall atchieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which may very eaſily be performed by vs in that God of his eſpeciall goodnes to our Nation, hath indued vs with ſingularitie of apprehenſion, dexteritie of inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and meanes for diſcipline, exceeding all the borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring countries of the world. There is an vſe and an abuſe of the beſt creatures, and we can not deny, as well by the aſſertion of God himſelfe, who in the creation ſaw all that he had made to be good, but that they were all made for the comfort for the ſeruice and for the vſe of man. If we
<pb facs="tcp:21300:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:6"/>then neglecting the vſe, doe fall into the abuſe of thoſe good creatures, and make them euill and hurtfull to vs: that followeth that wee contradict God in his purpoſe: we alter the nature and qualitie of the creature, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from our ſelues, that precedency and ſuperioritie, which God hath giuen to man ouer thoſe creatures: how doe we abaſe our ſelues from that ſoueraigntie which God hath giuen vs: who ſaid <hi>(let man rule and haue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer all creatures on the earth,</hi> when we ſuffer a poore inanimate creature, ſo to conquer and ouercome vs, that we lye grouelling on the earth ſpeechleſſe: nay ſometimes lifeleſſe (ouer come by the ſtrength of a Grape a weake and feeble ſubſtance) we all deſire (as good reaſon we haue) to extenuate the power and kingdome of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than: but I dare boldly affirme, he gaineth more ſoules by this deadly ſinne of Drunkenneſſe, then by all the ſinnes of the world: and hath drowned and ſwallowed vp more in this gulfe, then were drowned in the generall deluge of <hi>Noahs</hi> floud. Lend me onely thy good will, for my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of thy ſafety, which thou mayeſt haue or not haue at thine Election. But better it were to forbeare to reade this ſame, vnleſſe thou practiſe the ſame in thy life and conuerſation: Which thing grant both thy ſelfe and me, hoping thou wilt pray for me, as I haue done for thee, leauing thy will to Gods directions.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21300:6"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS BANE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F according to the ſaying of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> that he which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth but one ſinne is to be rewarded with damnation, and according to the ſaying of Saint <hi>Iohn,
<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.8.</note> he which ſinneth is of the Diuell,</hi> What ſhall we thinke of thoſe deſperate perſons? Nay rather monſters of men, which through the loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vice of Drunkenneſſe commit all manner of ſinne: For <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, <hi>Drunkenneſſe is a monſter with many heads:</hi> As firſt, <hi>filthy talke:</hi> Secondly, <hi>Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Wrath;</hi> Fourthly, <hi>Murther;</hi> Fiftly <hi>Swearing;</hi> Sixtly, <hi>Curſing.</hi> If theſe be the chiefe heads that procede from the polluted body of this vgly <hi>Monſter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Filthy talke, the firſt bead of Drunkennes.</note> let vs trie them by the touchſtone of the holy Scripture, and ſee how they are allowed of thereby. And firſt concerning <hi>filthy talke,</hi> is is ſaid to the <hi>Counthians, that filthy ſpeakers and raylers ſhall not inherite the Kingdome of God:</hi> and the fourth to
<pb facs="tcp:21300:7"/>the <hi>Epheſians</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> forbids vs to haue any <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt communication to proceed forth of our mouthes,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.29.30.</note> but that which is good to the vſe of edifying, that it may mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter grace to the hearers.</hi> And alſo we muſt put away all bitterneſſe and euill ſpeaking: And further the fift to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> wiſheth that <hi>no filthineſſe nor fooliſh talking,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.4.</note> no not ſo much as <hi>ieſting</hi> ſhould ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee vſed, or named among Chriſtians. But from the mouthes of Drunkards what idle talke, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſpeech, blaſphemous oathes, and prophane words are vſed, no Chriſtian eares can with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence endure, but with griefe of minde, vexation of ſpirit, yea with both horrour and terrour to the ſoule of man. The greateſt curſe that euer fell on mankinde ſince the floud came by <hi>Drunkenneſſe,</hi> as appeareth in <hi>Geneſis</hi> by <hi>Noah</hi> (the godlieſt man then liuing) auoiding all other ſinnes,
<note place="margin">Gen 9.25</note> yet was vnawares taken with this vice of Ebrietie, and curſed his own ſonne with the bitter and perpetuall curſe of ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, Saying, <hi>Curſed be Canaan, a ſeruant of ſeruants ſhall he be to all his brethren.</hi> Which thing of ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude was neuer either heard or ſpoken off, although the world had then beene the ſpace of 1656. yeres: to the which curſe, God ſaying Amen, added alſo nakednes to the poſterity of <hi>Cham,</hi> as appeareth this day by the <hi>Virginians,</hi> and <hi>Indians</hi> being by the beſt Authors of Antiquitie noted to come from that <hi>Cham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nakednes and ſeruitude are hereditary curſe to all drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kardes &amp; their poſterity.</note> and ſurely by the ſlauerie and beggerie that happeneth generally to all that vſeth this vice I can thinke no other of it, but that it is a curſe heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie to all Drunkards themſelues, or at leaſt to their poſteritie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21300:7"/>
            <p>Now concerning the Deſcription of the ſecond head of this <hi>Monſter Drunkenneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fornication ſecond head.</note> which is <hi>Forniea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> The Apoſtle in the ſixt chapter to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be not deceiued, neither Fornicators, nor Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, nor Wantons, nor Buggerers,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9.15 18.19.20.</note> ſhall inherite the Kingdome of heauen:</hi> And in the 15. verſe he ſaith, <hi>Know yee not that your bodies are the members of Chriſt, ſhall I then take the members of Chriſt, and make them the members of an Harlot: Flye fornication, euery ſinne that a man doth is without the body, but hee that committeth Fornication, ſinneth againſt his owne body. Know yee not that the body is the Temple of the holy Ghoſt which is in you, whom ye haue of God? And yee are not your owne: for ye are bought for a price: therefore glorifie God in your body, and in your ſpirit, for they are Gods.</hi> Which being thus, what glory can that partie ſhew vnto God in his ſpirit that hath neither vſe of body nor ſence: for as <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaith, <hi>Reaſon departeth, when drinke poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth the braine.</hi> Thriſe worthy is this ſaying of the Philoſopher, and fit to be noted with golden let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: <hi>Cum tibi ſiue Deus, ſiue mater rerum omnium Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura dederit animum quo nihil eſt preſtantius ſic teipſum (O homo) ab abiicies at que proſternes vt nihil inter te &amp; quadrupedem aliquem potes intereſſe? Wheu as God hath giuen thee a liuing ſoule which excelleth all things (O man) wilt thou ſo much abaſe and diſgrace thy ſelfe, that thou wilt make no difference betwixt thy ſelfe and a bruit beaſt, for Drunkenneſſe doth not onely diſgrace, but euen ſlayeth the ſoule of man:</hi> according to <hi>Zeno</hi> his ſaying, <hi>It is not Death that deſtroyeth the ſoule, but a bad life.</hi> But to returne to the vice of <hi>Fornication,</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>For this is the will</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:8"/>led a man he ſhould be ſlaine for it, and further to ſet out the greatneſſe of this ſinne, and fearing they might bee tempted through briberie to ſpare the murtherer, he ſaith, <hi>moreouer yee ſhall take no recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for the life of the murderer,
<note place="margin">Num. 25.16.19.20.31.32</note> which is worthy to die, but he ſhall be put to death:</hi> The land where the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is done is ſo much pollnted, that there is no way to cleanſe it, but by the bloud of him that ſhed it. And ſurely it is ſeldome or neuer knowne that a Murtherer went in peace to his graue, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by <hi>Abimelech,</hi> who after hee had killed his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenty brethren, although God ſuffered him for a time to liue and to rule all Iſrael, yet at length hee died miſerably, and was ſlaine by the hands of a woman. <hi>Zimri</hi> murdered <hi>Elah,</hi> but afterward by Gods iuſt iudgement was forced to burne himſelfe.
<note place="margin">1 Kin. 19 &amp; 18</note> But this vnnaturall ſinne, this monſtrous deede, this abhorred fact of Murther is by no accident or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſo often committed as through Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not onely by Drunkards vpon others, but alſo many times through Gods heauy wrath vpon Drunkards themſelues, as by too many examples I am able to make proofe as well of the one as of the other.</p>
            <p>And firſt to begin with that high and mighty Monarch of the world <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great,
<note place="margin">Murders in Drunkenes.</note> who in the beginning of his Raigne was ſo temperate that he refuſed the Cookes and Paſterers of the Queene of <hi>Caria:</hi> ſaying, he had better then they were <hi>(viz.)</hi> for his dinner early riſing, and for his ſupper a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate dinner, notwithſtanding through the viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manners, and lewd cuſtomes of the Perſians, he
<pb facs="tcp:21300:8"/>was ſo much giuen at laſt vnto the exceſſe of drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he propounded ſixe hundred crownes for a reward to him that drunke moſt, <hi>called a cup of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, being of a great bigneſſe after his owne name: which cup when he offered vnto</hi> Caliſthenes <hi>one of his fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, he refuſed, ſaying, that he which dranke with</hi> Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander <hi>had neede of Aſculapius,</hi> at which words the King feeling himſelfe touched, and being in his drinke was ſo incenſed againſt him, that hee cauſed him immediately to be put in a cage with dogges (where hee poyſoned himſelfe) afterwards being perſwaded by a common Strumpet named <hi>Thais,</hi> he burnt <hi>Percipolis</hi> the chiefe Citie in <hi>Perſia,</hi> and which was worſt in his intemperancie killed his deere friend <hi>Clytus:</hi> for which bloudy deede after he came to himſelfe, he wept and faſted three dayes, and would had he been permitted haue ſlaine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. In this deede of <hi>Alexander.,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seneca. Epiſt.</hi> 59</note> the ſaying of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> is verified. <hi>Ebrietas vnius horae hilaram Inſaniam longi temporis tedio penſat. Drunkenneſſe requireth one houres merry madnes, with a long tedious time of ſorrow and repentance.</hi> The ſon of <hi>Cyril</hi> being drunk, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſlew that holy man his father, and mother alſo great with childe: hee hurt his two ſiſters, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floured one of them, which fearefull example is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make the haire of our head ſtand vpright, as often as any occaſion is offered vnto vs; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we might fall into any inconuenience through the allurement of drinking. But I may leaue off For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine examples, and recite too many of like nature in our owne Nation, <hi>William Purcas</hi> in Eſſex, <hi>Anno</hi> 1615. in his Drunkenneſſe being rebuked by his
<pb facs="tcp:21300:9"/>mother for his vice moſt cruelly and vnnaturally kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her. <hi>Anderſon</hi> in his drunkenneſſe killed a boy and was hanged for the ſame in <hi>May</hi> 1616. But as I haue recited theſe few, ſo could I make mention of multitudes and examples of the ſame nature. For I fully perſwade my ſelfe, that there is not a citie nor market towne in England, but it would appeare (if the records of aſsiſes were ſearched) that there hath not beene ſome one or more ſlaine in it through Drunkennes, which is according to the old ſaying, <hi>Plus crapula quam gladio, more men haue died thorugh intemperancie then with the ſword,</hi> for ſuch is the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of exceſſiue drinking that it intoxicateth and boyleth the braines, benummeth the ſences, infee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the ioynts and ſynewes, and bringeth a man into a lethergie,
<note place="margin">Drunkards murthered. King. 16, 9.</note> the whole body into Dropſies, Gowtes, Palſies, Opoplexes and ſuch like. But now to returne and ſpeake of them that haue been ſlaine in their drinke. <hi>Elah</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> being drunke in <hi>Tirzah</hi> was murthered by <hi>Zimri</hi> his ſeruant. <hi>Amon</hi> one of <hi>Dauids</hi> vngracious ſonnes was ſlaine by his Brother <hi>Abſolons</hi> commandement,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 13.18, 29.</note> when hee was full of Wine. <hi>Fliolmus</hi> King of the <hi>Gothes</hi> was ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to drinking, that he would ſit a great part of the night quaffing and carowſing with his ſeruants, and as on a time hee ſate after his accuſtomed and beaſtly manner carowſing with them: his ſeruants being as drunke as their Maſter; threw their maſter King in ſport into a great veſſell full of drinke that was ſet in the middeſt of the Hall, where he moſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculouſly and miſerably ended his dayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtine Lachimer</hi> reporteth that in <hi>Germany</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:21300:9"/>the yere 1549. there were three companions in ſuch a iollity, after they had taken in their cups accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their brutiſh manner of that countrey, that with a cole they painted the Diuell in the wall, and dranke freely vnto him, and talked to him as though he had beene perſonally preſent, the next morning they were found all ſtrangled and dead, as the flye playeth ſo long with the Candle, vntill at length ſhe burneth her ſelfe: ſo theſe men delighted in ſinne, and dallied with the Diuell ſo long vntill they brought themſelues to vtter ruine and deſtruction. Which horrible and fearefull example, is ſufficient to ſtrike terrour and amazement to the greateſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowſers of our age, to feare leaſt Gods heauy wrath ſhould bee incenſed againſt them, and ſo deliuer them ouer to Sathan, and ſuffer them to die in their drunkenneſſe, and as the tree falleth ſo he lyeth.
<note place="margin">Luk. 21.34.35.36.</note> But I will conclude with our Sauiours words, the 21. of S. <hi>Luke, Cauete autem vobis, Take heede to your ſelues leſt at any time your hearts bee oppreſſed with ſurfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Drunkenneſſe, leſt the laſt day come on you vnawares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to proceede to the fift Head which is ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring forbidden by Gods commandement both in <hi>Exodus</hi> and <hi>Deuteronomie,
<note place="margin">Swearing. Exod: 20.1. Deut. 5.</note> Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine, for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſſe that taketh his name in vaine.</hi> Which is ſo frequently vſed among Drunkards that ſcarce ſix words are vſed amongſt them without an oath, and that vpon moſt vaine and idle occaſions, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that you haue not pledged me, or your cup was not full, or you left a ſnuffe in the bottome, and vpon ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:21300:10"/>like ſwaggering occaſions, the Name of God is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in vaine, and with ſuch horrible, deteſtable, and blaſpheamous oathes (as me thinketh) I am affraid to mention, being by all the parts of Chriſt, as by his Life, Death, Paſſion, Fleſh, Heart, Wounds, Bloud, Bones, Armes, Sides, Guts, Nayles, Foote: as if they went to crucifie Chriſt a new: who while hee was vpon the earth, forbid it vtterly in theſe words: <hi>I ſay vnto you,
<note place="margin">Mat. 4.34.35.36, 37.</note> ſweare not at all, neither by heauen for it is the Throne of God, nor yet by the earth, for it is his ſo teſtcole: nor yet by Ieruſalem, for it is the Citie of the great King: Ne ther ſhalt thou ſweare by the head, becauſe thou canſt not make one hayre white or blacke. But your communication ſhall be yea,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 19.</note> Nay nay?</hi> In <hi>Leuitious</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall not ſweare by my name falſly, neither ſhalt thou defile the name of thy God, I am the Lord.</hi> I feare me we ſhall haue iuſt cauſe to complaine with <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 23.10.</note> that <hi>becauſe of oathes the land mourneth,</hi> In <hi>Zecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah</hi> we may finde that ſwearers are noted in a book and that euery one that ſweareth,
<note place="margin">Zach: 5.3.4.</note> ſhall be cut off as well on this ſide, as on that ſide, <hi>(viz:)</hi> whereſoeuer he be in the world, and <hi>that the curſe of God will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the houſe of him that falſly ſweareth, and it ſhall remaine in the middeſt of his houſe, and ſhall conſum it both with the tymber and the ſtones thereof.</hi> The wiſe King perceiuing the great danger that commeth by ſwearing,
<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 23.9.11.</note> warneth vs not to accuſtome our ſelues to ſwearing, for in it are many fals, neither take vp for a cuſtome the meaning of the Holy One, for thou ſhalt not be vnpuniſht for ſuch things: for as a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant which is oftpuniſht, cannot be without ſome ſcarrè, ſo hee that ſweareth and nameth God conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually
<pb facs="tcp:21300:10"/>ſhall not be faultleſſe, man that vſeth much ſwearing, ſhall bee filled with wickednes, and the plague ſhall neuer goe from his houſe, when he ſhall offend his faults ſhal be vpon him, and if he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge not his ſinne, he maketh a double offence and if he ſweare in vaine, he ſhall not be innocent, but his houſe ſhal be full of plagues.
<note place="margin">Iam: 5, 12</note> Saint <hi>Iames</hi> wiſheth vs before all things, to auoide ſwearing, <hi>either by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or by the earth, or by any other oath:</hi> Let all ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers take heede, although God ſuffers them for a time, leſt they bee ſuddenly ſtricken with death as many haue beene, and then vengeance waiting at the doore, at the houre of death, and when their bodies ſhall be without life, their ſoules ſhall bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtingly without God. How did God puniſh the oath broken by the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam: 21, 1.9</note> not onely with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine three yeeres together, but with the death of <hi>Sauls</hi> ſeuen ſonnes, who were hanged vp openly in the mountaines. See what the Lord ſaith in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> of <hi>Zedechiah</hi> that hee ſhall not proſper for breaking his oath: <hi>As I liue,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 17: 15.16.19.</note> I will ſurely bring mine oath that he hath deſpiſed, and my couenant that he hath broken vpon his owne head:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King: 25.2.</note> and ſo it came to paſſe <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi> by an armie ouercame him, ſlew his ſonnes before his face, put out both his eyes, and carried him to <hi>Babel.</hi> But in theſe later times, and in this our land I may ſhew very many examples, as of Earle <hi>Godwin,</hi> who wiſhing at the Kings table that the bread hee eate might choke him, if he were guilty of <hi>Alphreds</hi> death, whom hee had before ſlaine: was preſently choked and fell downe dead.
<note place="margin">Fox: actes and monu.</note> Wee may reade in the Acts and Monuments of one <hi>Iohn Peter,</hi> a horrible
<pb facs="tcp:21300:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:12"/>ſwearer, with whom it was vſuall to ſay, if it be not true, <hi>I pray God I may rot ere I dye.</hi> To which God ſaid, A men, and ſo he rotted away indeed, and died miſerably. Laſtly, witneſſe the example of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uingman in <hi>Lincolne-ſhire,</hi> who for euery trifle had an vſe to ſweare no leſſe oath then (Gods precious bloud) he would not bee warned by his friends to leaue it, at laſt he was viſited with grieuous ſicknes, in the time whereof he could not be perſwaded to repent of it, but hearing the Bell to Toll, in the very anguiſh of death, hee ſtarted vp in his bed, and ſwore by his former oath that Bell tolled for him. Wherevpon immediately the bloud aboundantly from all the ioynts of his body as it were in ſtreams did iſſue out moſt fearefully, from mouth, noſe, wriſts, knees, heeles and toes, with all other ioynts not one left free, and ſo dyed. Theſe and ſuch like examples, and fearefull warnings from heauen, are ſufficient to terrifie the hearts of all Drunkards whoſe tongues being ſet on fire of hell,
<note place="margin">Iam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6, 7.8, 9.</note> ſpeake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing without an oath, and Drunkards vſually fall into the ſinnes of the tongue, againſt which S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh ſo bitterly,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 141.3.</note> and <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Set a watch, O Lord before my mouth, and keepe the doore of my lips:</hi> With whoſe ſaying in the 50. Pſalme, I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and wiſh all Drunkards and Swearers to pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his words:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.21.</note> 
               <hi>Conſider of theſe things yee that forget God, leſt he teare you in pieces, and there be none to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to ſpeake of the ſixt and laſt Head,
<note place="margin">Sixtly Curſing.</note> which is <hi>Curſing: Dauid</hi> noting the vileneſſe of this ſinne: Reputeth thoſe perſons that vſe this vice to thinke
<pb facs="tcp:21300:12"/>there is no God to yeeld them vengeance for their wickednes, noteth them in the 14. Pſalme, which beginneth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.6.</note> 
               <hi>The foole hath ſaid in his heart there is no God:</hi> and ſo going forward to the 6. verſe, ſaith, <hi>Their mouth is full of curſing and bitterneſſe:</hi> And in the hundreth and ninth Pſalme, hee ſheweth that God will neuer bleſſe them that curſe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 109.17.18.</note> But that he ſhall be curſed of all people: <hi>As hee loued Curſing ſo ſhall it come vnto him, and as it loued not Bleſsing, ſo ſhall it be farre from him: as he clothed himſelfe with cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing like a rayment, ſo ſhall it come into his bones: Let it be vnto him as a garment to couer him, and for a girdle wherewith he ſhall be alwaies girded. Dauid</hi> did rightly terme Curſing the girdle of the Drunkard. For hee is compaſſed about both at home and abroad with curſings. At home he is curſed of his Wife, for waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of her portion, and bringing her in contempt, penury and miſery: Of his Family, becauſe hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraudeth their bellies, through his waſting and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perflous exceſſe abroad: The good Wiſe is forced to pinch her houſhould at home: Yea, of his owne children (if not in his life time by his daughters,) for that they are not through his vnthriſtineſſe and baſe manner of liuing, preferred in marriage. Yet by his ſonnes after his death, for ſpending their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie (by ſucceſſion due to them:) and not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them education: How many men haue I heard ſay, I am bound to curſe the time, that euer my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was a company keeper, which had he not been I might haue proued a Scholler, or I ſhould haue had ſuch lands or ſuch liuings, which my father ſpent in his ſolly: Yea the very nouriſhers of his
<pb facs="tcp:21300:13"/>vices themſelues, when his money is ſpent doe curſe him, the Hoſt and Hoſteſſe curſe him, becauſe he troubleth their houſe (being pierce penileſſe) and not giue place to other gueſts: that are full fraught: The Tapſters curſe him, becauſe hee cals for Beere, and runnes in ſcore: the Chamberlaines they curſe him, for tumbling the beds, polluting the roome, and he curſeth them as faſt, for decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him of his money, are not Drunkards accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Dauids</hi> ſaying, girded about with curſes: Which girdle the Diuell claſpeth about him ſo faſt, it is to be feared without repentance and the great mercy of God, it will neuer be vnlooſed vntill hee hath him in hell, where with the damned ſoules he will be forced to cry:</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>O dolor, ô Rabies, ô ſtridor dentium &amp; Ingence,</l>
                  <l>Luctus &amp; Inferni meluendus carceris horror.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With griefe, with rage, with gnaſhing teeth, and howling great,</l>
                  <l>In this infernall lake and horride place my ſoule is fret.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the third to the <hi>Coloſians</hi> bids vs to <hi>put away all malicious curſed ſpeaking forth of our mouthes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.8.</note> and to the <hi>Romans</hi> hee ſaith, <hi>Bleſſe but curſe not.</hi> And ſurely the Diuell and deſtruction waites at the doore, when wee fall into this humour of cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<note place="margin">Marke. 14.17.</note> as appeareth by <hi>Peter,</hi> before hee denied his Maſter, Our bleſſed Sauiour. Firſt hee began to <hi>curſe,</hi> and then he <hi>ſwore,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I know not this man of whom ye ſpeake. Goliah</hi> before he was killed of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.43.</note> fell a <hi>curſing,</hi> and ſo died in this wickednes. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> held this fault ſo great in <hi>Shemi,</hi> for curſing him
<pb facs="tcp:21300:13"/>that euen vpon his death-bed: he tooke order with <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne to put <hi>Shemei</hi> to death for the ſame.
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.5.13 <hi>Shemei</hi> curſing. 1 King. 2.8.9.46. His death.</note> 
               <hi>Behold with thee is</hi> Shemei <hi>which curſed me with a horrible curſe, therefore thou ſhalt cauſe his hoare head to goe downe to the graue in bloud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the heads that ſpring from this polluted Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, are ſo deteſtable dangerous, and damnable: (as by the fore-recited places of Scripture is declared:) it is requifite (that the noyſome and infectious poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to mankinde) which doth proceede from the nature and condition of this Monſter ſhould plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be made manifeſt, and deſcribed to the world:
<note place="margin">Drunkenes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined.</note> And therefore to define it, <hi>Drunkenneſſe is a vice which ſtirreth vp luſt, griefe, anger, and madneſſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſheth the memory, opinion and vnderſtanding, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a man the picture of a beaſt, and twiſe a childe, becauſe hee can neither ſtand nor ſpeake.</hi> Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ad ſacram Ebrietas eſt flagitiorum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium mater culparumque materia, &amp;c. Drunkenneſſe is the mother of outrages, the matter of faults, the roote of crimes, the fountaine of vice, the intoxicate or of the head, the quelling of the ſences, the tempeſt of the tongue, the ſtorme of the body, the ſhipwracke of chaſtitie, loſſe of time, voluntarie madneſſe, an ignominious languor, the filthineſſe of manners, the diſgrace of life, the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſoule:</hi> Were there no more to be ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Drunkennes then the words of this Holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (if they were duely conſidered) my thinkes it ſhould bee enough to deterre any Chriſtian man from that vice. <hi>Cyrus</hi> being but a childe and a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, when he was asked by his Grandfather <hi>Aſtya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> why he dranke no Wine at a great Feaſt, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:21300:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:15"/>
               <hi>he tooke it to be poyſon, becauſe ſaid he thoſe at the laſt Feaſt that dranke it were depriued of their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and ſences:</hi> The <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> would often ſhew their children ſuch as were drunke, to the end they ſhould learne to hate that vice. Theſe being but children and Heathens by ſeeing ill examples loathed the vice, and grew the better. Wee being men and Chriſtians on the contrarie, by ſeeing ill examples loue the vice, and grow the worſe. For before we were acquainted with the lingring wars of the Low-Countries, Drunkennes was held in the higheſt degree of hatred that might be amongſt vs: For if by chance any one had been ouertaken with his cups, and gone reeling in the ſtreets, or lyen ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vnder a Table, we would haue ſpit at him as a Toade, and cald him drunken Swine, and warnd all our friends out of his company: but now it is grown for a cuſtome and the faſhion of our age, euen in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Townes, Villages, I euen amongſt the very Woods and Forreſts (as ſhall be ſpoken of hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) nay it is mounted ſo high, that men muſt in a manner bluſh and be aſhamed as much to ſpeake of ſobrietie, or to be temperate, (in a thouſand com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies.) As in that happy time of our ancients, they were aſhamed of Ebrietie in others, or to be drunke themſelues. Why? He is reputed a Peſant, a ſlaue and a Bore, that will not take his liquor profound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: He is a man of no faſhion that cannot drinke <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per naculum,</hi> Carouſe the Hunters Hoope, quaffe Vpſey-freeſe croſſe, Bowſe in Permoyſaunt, in Pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lico, in Crambo, with Healthes, Gloues, Numpes, Frolicks and a thouſand ſuch dominering inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:21300:15"/>as by the Bell, by the Cards, by the Dye,
<note place="margin">A lottery vpon the card newly inuented for drinking.</note> by the Dozen, by the Yard, and ſo by meaſure wee drinke out of meaſure. Thus wee ſpend ſo great a time in carowſing, as though we did not drinke to liue, but liued to drinke: and for the further main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and vpholding of this moſt execrable vice, there are in London drinking ſchooles: ſo that drunkenneſſe is profeſſed with vs as a liberall Arte and Science: all Chriſtians haue iuſt cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, and to crie out that we haue receiued by the Low Countries the moſt irreparable damadge that euer fell on the Kingdome of England.</p>
            <p>Drunkards now a dayes make meetings and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of drinking,
<note place="margin">Iſa. 56.18.</note> and incourage one an other there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, according to the ſaying of <hi>Eſay: Come I will bring Wine, and we will fill our ſelues with ſtrong drink, and to morrow ſhall be as this day, and much more aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant.</hi> But you that reioyce thus in your wickedneſſe and in your abominable Drunkenneſſe heare and tremble at the reward prouided for you, and men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by S. <hi>Iohn,
<note place="margin">Reu. 23.8.25.27.</note> Your part is in the lake which bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth with fire and brimſtone which is the ſecond death. The gates of heauen ſhall he ſhut againſt you. For there ſhall no vncleane thing, nor none that worketh abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards ſhall neuer inherite the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi> And likewiſe to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> he ſaith, that <hi>Drunkards, ſhall not inherite the Kingdome of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.10. Gal. 5.21.</note> Theſe ſayings of the Apoſtles &amp; Euangeliſts are enough to ſtrike terrour to the ſoules of any Chriſtian man, and ſo farre to barre them from Drunkenneſſe, that rather then they would be in danger to fall into it, they
<pb facs="tcp:21300:16"/>would drink water as <hi>Daniel</hi> &amp; his fellows did,
<note place="margin">Dan. 12.</note> when they refuſed the Wine of the Kings Table. But your common Drunkards are no Chriſtians: For a true Chriſtian is the childe of light, and walketh in the light,
<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.6.7.8</note> and is ſober, but the Drunkard is the child of darkneſſe, and the workes which he doth are the workes of darkneſſe: And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for vs that we haue ſpent the time paſt of our life after the luſt of the Gentiles,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 4.3.</note> walking in Wantonneſſe, Luſts,
<note place="margin">Fit. 2.12.</note> Drunkenneſſe, Gluttonie, Drinkings, &amp;c.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus</hi> ſaith, <hi>that the grace of God that bringeth ſaluation to all men, hath appeared, and teacheth vs that we ſhould deny vngodlineſſe and worldly luſts, and that we ſhould liue ſoberly, and righteouſly, and godly in this World.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.8.</note> And in the third Chapter, <hi>It is a true ſaying, that they which beleeue in God muſt be carefull to ſhew forth good workes.</hi> Which makes plaine that Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards are no Chriſtians, and therefore not of God, for the Drunkard maketh his belly his God,
<note place="margin">Phil. 3.19.</note> becauſe he more diligently ſerues it, more better loues it, and more carefully pleaſeth it, then God himſelfe: And to ſpeake truely of him,
<note place="margin">A Drunkard ſit for nothing.</note> a Drunkard is vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for any honeſt ſeruice, and can make neither good Magiſtrate, nor good Subiect: ſeeing he can not rule others, that cannot rule himſelfe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rightly ſaid Saint <hi>Auguſtine; Ehrioſus cum obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet obſorbetur à vino, abominatur à Deo deſpicitur ab Angellis, decidetur ab hominibus deſtituetur à virtuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus confunditur à Daemonib conculcatur ab hominibus. When the Drunkard deuoureth Wine, hee is deuoured of Wine, hee is abominable to God, deſpiſed of the Angels, ſcorned of men, abandoned of vertue, confounded by the
<pb facs="tcp:21300:16"/>Diuels, and trampled vnder mens feete.</hi> If the inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience that followeth drunkenneſſe be ſo great; let vs ſearch out the benefits and pleaſures that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth thereby:
<note place="margin">The pleaſures that proceed of drinke.</note> and ſee whether they will counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile the precedent miſchiefes. And firſt I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the words of him that ſhewed the great force of drinke to <hi>Darius,
<note place="margin">1 Eſdras. 3.20.</note> It turneth euery thought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ioy and gladnes, ſo that one remembreth no manner of ſorrow nor debt.</hi> This is a moſt ſpeciall matter, that many men doe pretend to bee the cauſe of their drinking, becauſe they would comfort themſelues in their ſorrowes, either for that they are in debt, or their wiues, parents, or friends croſſe them. I muſt confeſſe drinke makes a man merry for the time, and quite forget his debt. For being drunke he thinketh himſelfe as rich as <hi>Croeſus,</hi> and as good as <hi>Alexander.</hi> But this ioy is deceiueable, falſe and fleeting; it is like a dream, aſhadow, for let him drink what he can, if it were a Hogs head, it payes not of his debt a halfe-penny, and when he comes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe he findes his body is ſicke, his time is loſt, his money ſpent, his credits crackt, he hath abuſed his God, wronged his wife, grieued his friends, and ſhamed himſelfe: here is an inch of pleaſure bought with an ell of paine, in like manner if thy parents or friends croſſe thee, and thou range from houſe to houſe, from Ale to Beere, from Beere to Wine, and ſo fill thy skin and head with liquor, to expell thy griefe, it will be no otherwiſe with the, then it was with King <hi>Saul,</hi> who <hi>while</hi> Dauid <hi>played with his Harpe was neuer vexed with the wickea ſpirit,
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.23. &amp;. 18; Chap. 10.</note> but when he ceaſed his play, the Diuell tormented him afreſh.</hi> So
<pb facs="tcp:21300:17"/>while the ſence is loſt and memory decayed, thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents are cleane forgot, but when thy drink hath played his part and force thereof is quite expelled: thy ſoules inſnared, thy mindes perplexed, thy griefes and diſcontents (as bad) or worſe then ere they were. I may fitly compare theſe ranging drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards to <hi>Virgils</hi> Hart:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quam procul incautam nemora inter creſsia fixit</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Paſtor agens telis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>— Illa fuga Siluas ſaltuſque peragrat dicteos</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>— haeret lateri lethalis arundo.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who ranging through the chace, ſome hunter ſhooting far by chance,</l>
                     <l>All vnawares hath ſmit, and in her ſide hath left his launce,</l>
                     <l>She faſt to wilderneſſe and woods doth draw and there complaines,</l>
                     <l>But vnderneath her ribs the deadly dart remaines.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore he doth moſt vnwiſely that hath any cauſe of griefe or diſcontent, and thinketh to put it away by drinking, or going to their merry compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, or that good fellow: for let him flye whether he will, he carries his diſcontent in his heart; Take Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> aduice, the ſecond to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it with patience, <hi>For our light affliction which is but for a moment,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Cor. 1.34, 4.17.</note> cauſeth vnto vs a farre more excellent and an eternall weight of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If thou art troubled with a ſcoulding wife, whoſe tongue I muſt needs ſay ſtingeth like a ſcorpion (and hee that can abide a curſt wife needes not to feare what company he liueth in) the bitter tempeſt of whoſe tongue I muſt confeſſe as forcibly driues a man out of his doores into euill company, as a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſtorm doth birds forth of the field into buſhes: enter into the Etemologie of her name, ſhe is called: in Latine <hi>Mulier quaſi mugire vix:</hi> In Engliſh <hi>a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb facs="tcp:21300:17"/>quaſi woe vnto man,</hi> She is as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.9,</note> 
               <hi>The portion of thy ſorrow which God hath allotted thee thy tormentor vpon earth to bring thy ſoule to heauen.</hi> For which malady: this is the beſt medicine:
<note place="margin">The remedy for a ſcolde.</note>
               <q>Vſibus edocto ſi quicquam credis amico.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Eyther to ſtop thine eares and not here her: or elſe to be ſilent, laugh at her, and not regard her: and not to ſeeke reuenge like the baſe ſonne of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man in Rome: who being taken in a robberie, and brought before a Iudge to bee arraigned, hee asked him whoſe ſonne he was: hee anſwered hee would not tell him, but ſaid hee was the ſonne of him that if he were hanged would ſurely be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for his death, and ſo was contented to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, that he might afterwards bee reuenged of the Iudge; and no otherwiſe doth hee that leaues his home, runnes beſſeling to an Ale-houſe,
<note place="margin">Mad men that goe to be drunke for woemens wordes.</note> damnes his ſoule, hurts his body, ſpends his time, waſts his goods, grieues his friends, beggers himſelfe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doeth his children, and all to be reuenged of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: (for her tongue in which there is no gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) wherefore that is to be borne with patience, which cannot be redreſſed with carefulneſſe. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers proteſt the delight they take in this vice is not for the drinke, but by reaſon of the company. To which I anſwere,
<note place="margin">Company the great cauſe of drunkennes.</note> that is a bad fellowſhip which brings vs into a league with vice, and makes vs to ſet vertue at vtter defiance, that is a wicked knot of friendſhip, which tyes vs to our damnation, and mad dotage, that rather then wee will part with wicked companions, we will in fooliſh kindnes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company them into hell. If thereforee our compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb facs="tcp:21300:18"/>delight in ſinne, let not vs delight in them, but flye their ſocietie,
<note place="margin">Exod. 23.2.</note> as being the Diuels aduocates to ſolicite vs into wickedneſſe, and let vs take heede whileſt we labor to maintaine friendſhip with men, we doe not proclaime omnitie againſt God. It is ſaid in <hi>Exodus,
<note place="margin">Eph. 57.11.</note> Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to doe euill.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> bids vs to <hi>haue no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip nor company with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe inſtruments of Sathan, but rather reproue them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.11.</note> And to the <hi>Corinthians: Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany not with a Drunkard, not ſo much as to eate with him, much leſſe to drinke. Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Bee not of the number of them which are bibbers of Wine, for the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and the feaſter ſhall be come poore,
<note place="margin">Pro. 23.</note> &amp;c.</hi> The Poet rightly ſaid:</p>
            <q>
               <p>Commencia turpia ſanctos. Corrumpunt mores, multi hoc periere veneno labimur in vitium &amp; facile ad peiora mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mur:</p>
               <p>Euill company doth corrupt good manners, and many haue periſhed by this miſchiefe, wee quickly ſlide into vice, and are eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwaded to become worſe and worſe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The greateſt benefit thou ſhalt receiue by theſe ſwaggering and deboyſt companions,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A</hi> drunkard ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cannot or will not doe any man good.</note> is faire words, but faint deeds, for the moſt part what they promiſe when they are drunke, they forget when they are ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: or elſe in their vaine-glorious humour, they promiſe higher matters then their low eſtate (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with prodigalitie) can performe, for</p>
            <q>
               <l>Prodigalitas eſt vas magnum ſine fundo ingens arca,</l>
               <l>Sine ſera omnia profundit, reponit nihil.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Prodigalitie is a huge veſſel without a bottome, a great cheſt without a locke, it drawes forth all things, it layes vp nothing.</hi> Your pot friendſhip, is no friendſhip: For
<pb facs="tcp:21300:18"/>as long as thou haſt good clothes on thy backe, and money in thy purſe, thou ſhalt haue friends plenty, and good fellowes flocke about thee: to giue thee drinke, when thou haſt too much before, and truely I thinke herevpon comes the name of goodfellow, <hi>quaſi</hi> goad fellow, becauſe hee forceth and goads his fellowes forward to be drunke with his perſwaſiue termes, as I dranke to you, I pray pledge me, you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonour me, you diſgrace mee, and with ſuch like words, doth vrge his conſorts forward to be drunke, as oxen being prickt with goads, are compeld and forced to draw the Waine. But to returne to their friendſhip, if thou art in want &amp; miſery, theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions will not know thee, and if by chance thou come in houſe where as they are, to ſhun thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany they ſtrait call, Chamberlaine giues a priuate roome? And he that before would ſpend a crowne vpon thee to make thee drunke, will not now in thy penury lend thee ſixe pence to make thee eate, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though for lacke of foode thou ſtarueſt in the ſtreet. But I will councell you with <hi>Naſh.</hi> All you that will not haue your braines twice ſodden,
<note place="margin">The fruits of drunkeneſſe.</note> your fleſh rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the Dropſie, that loue not to goe in greaſie dublets, ſtockings out at heeles, and weare Alehouſe daggers at your backes, leaue this company keeping this ſlabbering brauerie, that will make you haue ſtinking breathes, and your faces blowed like blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, deckt with pimples, your bodies ſmell like Brewers aprons. It will bring you in your old age to bee companions with none but <hi>Porters, Oaſtlers,</hi> and <hi>Carmen,</hi> to talke out of a Cage rayling as Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards are wont, a hundred boyes wondring about
<pb facs="tcp:21300:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:20"/>them: It is a moſt bewitching ſinne, and being once entred into, hard to forgoe. Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> compares it to the pit of hell, <hi>into which when one is once falling there is no redemption.</hi> Therefore you that are free from it reioyce and deſire God ſo to keep you: and you that are entring into it forgoe it in time, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Iam. 4.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Reſiſt the Diuell and hee will flie from you, draw neere to God, and he will draw neere to you.</hi> Take heede leſt you take a habite in it, and ſo it grow to a cuſtome, and then like the grand Drunkards of this age (of whom I know too many) you account it no ſinne: For, <hi>conſuetudo peccandi tollit ſenſum peccati, the cuſtome of ſinning taketh away the feeling of ſinne.</hi> But with theſe Drunkards I haue not to doe, for no admoniſhment, but baniſhment will make them leaue it: For I feare the Lord hath done by them, as by <hi>Ieremiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 51.39.</note> he threatneth the Babylonians, <hi>he hath giuen them ouer to a perpetuall drunkennes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others excuſe themſelues, and thinke they are free from this vice, becauſe (through the ſtrength of their braines and bodies) they can carry more then others: and boaſt although they dranke as much as any in the company, and that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts were drunke. Yet they were freſh enough: it is a ſmall conqueſt they haue got, when in exceſſiue drinking they haue ouercome all their compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: ſeeing in conquering they are ouercome, and are ſhamefully foyled and ouerthrowne by Sathan, their chiefe enemy, whileſt they triumph in a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken victory ouer their friends: theſe men for want of vertue in them bragge of their vice: but <hi>Habakuk</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Haba. 2.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>woe vnto him that giueth his neighbour drinke,
<pb facs="tcp:21300:20"/>thou ioyneſt thine heate, and makest him drunken that thou maiſt ſee his priuities:
<note place="margin">Iſa 28.3.</note> The Lords right hand ſhall be turned vnto thee, and ſhameful ſpuing ſhall be for thy glory.</hi> And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">Prouer. 11.</note> 
               <hi>The crowne and the pride of the Drunkard ſhall be troden vnder feete.</hi> And in the fift chapter hee pronounceth a <hi>woe vnto them which riſe vp early to follow Drunkennes, and to them that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue vntill night, &amp;c.</hi> The Philoſopher ſaith: <hi>Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la capitalior peſtis hominibus à natura data eſt quam E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietas, nam, ex hac fonte prodit quicquid eſt in homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num vite ſcelerum &amp; calamitatum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nature neuer ſent amongſt men a more deadlier plague then Drunkennes, for it is the well-ſpring from whence floweth all manner of miſchiefe, and calamitie that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens to men.</hi> Wine hath as much force as fire, for as ſoone as it hath ouertaken any it diſpatcheth him: For it diſcloſeth the ſecrets of the ſoule, and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth the whole minde. A drunken gouernour and ruler of any thing whatſoeuer, bringeth all to ruine and ouerthrow, whether it be a Ship, or a Wagon, or Armie, or any other thing committed to his charge: The conſideration whereof made the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher ſay, when the Wine is in a man, hee is as a running Coach without a Coachman. Therefore they that delight (not onely to ſee) but alſo to force their neighbors to ſinne in this vice by vrging them to drinke more then they would onely to pledge them, doe no otherwiſe then if they made it their glory and paſtime, to ſee God diſhonoured, his name blaſpheamed, his creatures abuſed, and their friends and companions damned. To reioyce to ſee a man drunk, is no otherwiſe then to be glad to ſee a
<pb facs="tcp:21300:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:21"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:22"/>
               <hi>the vngodly and ſinner appeare.</hi> Theſe men are imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of <hi>Tiberius</hi> and <hi>Vitellius,</hi> moſt beaſtly and luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, <hi>Emperours</hi> of Rome: who <hi>were drunke and rioted all night, and ſleepe and reſted all day.</hi> The firſt, for his beaſtly conditions of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> was called <hi>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suetonius.</note> of <hi>Claudius ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dius,</hi> of <hi>Nero, Mero:</hi> in his drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe be cauſed Rome to be fired, yet before he died (as a iuſt plague vnto him) he <hi>was forced to drink puddle water. and commended the ſame for an admirable drinke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llius. Reguat</hi> but eight-monthes.</note> and for feare of the Citizens puniſhment, was forced to ſtab himſelfe: the other was drawne through the ſtreets with a halter about his necke, and ſhamefully put to death: a right reward and good example for drunken Magiſtrates, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours. But I could wiſh that ryotous perſons, would note and take example by the gouernment of <hi>Antonius Pius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>T. Anto. P.</hi> was the 16. Emper. of <hi>Rome</hi> 23. yeeres.</note> in whoſe time (when hee percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) the people of Rome giuen to drinke without meaſure, he made a law that none ſhould ſell Wine, but the Apothecaries in their ſhops, and onely for the ſicke and diſeaſed. Or behold the gouernment of <hi>Alexander Seuerus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alex.</hi> 26. Empe. Rom. 13. yeeres</note> who quite purged Rome from all the filthy vices, and fowle enormities, bred in the time of his predeceſſor, <hi>Helyogabalus,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced it to the ancient and ciuill gouernment, that <hi>Cicero</hi> writeth of in his Booke of lawes, wherein he affirmeth, that no Roman durſt goe in the ſtreetes. If that he bare not a ſhew in his hand, whereon hee did liue. In conſideration thereof, the <hi>Conſull did be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re a Battle Axe before him, the Praetors a Hat in the maner of a Coyfe: the Tribunes a Mace: the Cutlers a Sword, the Taylors a payre of Sheares: the Smithes a
<pb facs="tcp:21300:22"/>Hammer: the Orators a Booke;</hi> not permitting that thoſe that were Maſters of Sciences, ſhould bee ſchollars of vices: (in ſuch ſort that <hi>Marcus Aureli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in making mention of the ancient diligence of the <hi>Romans,</hi> writeth that <hi>they did alſo employ with ſuch a zeale their labours and trauely, that in Rome could not be found an idle perſon, to carry a letter two or three dayes iourney.</hi> But if this law of the <hi>Romans</hi> were in force with vs, how many thouſands (if they made ſhew of the trade and arte they profeſſed) would be forced to goe vp and down with quart pots in their hands: our Nation is ſo polluted with this vice of Drunkenneſſe, that the great drinkings of forraine Countries compared to ours, are but ſippings. We haue them that drinke more in a yeere,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maximillion</hi> the Emp. is ſayd to deuour forry pound of fleſh, &amp; drink a hogſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of wine in one day.</note> then <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>million</hi> the Emperour: And others that drink more at a draught, then any Hackney horſe. The hiſtorie that <hi>Paulus Diacrus</hi> reporteth (of the drinking of foure Lumbards, although a thing to all the hearers in former ages reputed monſtrous, yet compared to the drinkings of our times, it is ſcarce maruellous:) He ſaith, <hi>there were foure old men that made a banquet, in the which they dranke the yeeres of one another,</hi> after the manner as followeth: <hi>They ordained to drinke two to two, and counted their age of yeeres that each of them had, and he that dranke to his companion ſhould drinke ſo many times, as he had liued yeeres:</hi> and the yongeſt of theſe foure was eight and fifty yeeres old: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond threeſcore and three: the third foureſcore and ſeuen: the fourth foureſcore and twelue: ſo that he that dranke leaſt dranke eight and fifty taſters of Wine: Although theſe drinkings were ſtrange,
<pb facs="tcp:21300:23"/>monſtrous &amp; vnnaturall, and the draughts many in number, yet they were not great in quantity: nor like the draught that one of <hi>Sleuent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> made,
<note place="margin">A towne within two miles of Abington in Barkhamſtead.</note> who is yet liuing, he dranke a peck at a draught: one alſo a <hi>Dier</hi> of <hi>Barkhamſteed</hi> in <hi>Hartfordſhire</hi> did the like. I haue ſeene a company amongſt the very Woods and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, drinking for a muggle, in ſuch exceſſiue maner, that in my opinion it farre excelled the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Lumbards. For ſixe haue determined to trie their ſtrengths who could drinke moſt glaſſes for the muggle. The firſt drinkes a glaſſe of a pint, the ſecond two, the next three, and ſo euery one multiplyeth till the laſt taketh ſixe. Then the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth againe and taketh ſeuen, and in this manner they drinke thrice a peece round, euery man taking a glaſſe more then his fellow, ſo that hee that dranke leaſt: which was, the firſt dranke one and twentie pints, and the ſixt man thirty ſixe: which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the number of draughts were leſſe then the Lumbards, yet the quantitie of drinke was farre more. But if they hap to go a fourth about (as theſe Forreſters are like enough to bee ſoone ready em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barqued in this bold aduenture for hel) Then they farre exceede the drinkings of the Lumbards, in quantitie and qualitie, and for the ſame worthy to be canonized, fit Saints for the Diuell. And to ſpeak a truth concerning the manner of liuing of theſe Forreſters (as well the inhabitants of the new For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, as the Forreſt of Windſor) there is no place in England giuen to more frequent Ebrious meetings, and continuall drinkings, then they are: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though one may trauel a whole day abroad in theſe
<pb facs="tcp:21300:23"/>ſolitarie places, and not finde a man to guide him in his way. Yet if one returne to their ſcattering Villages, and loane houſes, you ſhall ſcarce goe a furlong, but he ſhall finde great plenty of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſtore of directers, to bring a man out of his wit: For there is not a Hamlet amongſt them, but is furniſhed with three or foure Alehouſes at the leaſt: Nay ſcarce a lone Cottage, but is a typ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſe, and theſe continually haunted with true Ale-Knights, that cry out, they had rather drinke forth their eyes, then the wormes ſhould eate them out, according to the Poet:
<q>
                  <l>Valebetis inquit ocelli</l>
                  <l>Namque ſatis vidi non ſatis vſque bibi:</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>M. <hi>Camden</hi> in his Britania reciteth, that it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Blacke booke of th'Exchequer, that a Forreſt is a ſafe harbour and abiding place of Deere or Beaſts, not of any ſort whatſoeuer: but of wilde and ſuch as delight in Woods, (and herevpon a Forreſt hath the name (as one would ſay <hi>Fereſta,</hi> that is a Station of wilde Beaſts: and likewiſe I thinke the inhabitants of theſe places, learne their ſauage manners, and brutiſh behauiour, becauſe they conuerſe chiefely with Beaſts: For they haue no Magiſtrates, nor they will hire no Miniſters, for they goe ten times to an Ale-houſe, before they goe once to a Church: Well they may bee likened to <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the yonger, who was ſometimes more then nine dayes drunke together, but in the end he loſt his eſtate, and it is to be feared (vnleſſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and amend, their hap will bee as hard for
<pb facs="tcp:21300:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:24"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:25"/>heauen, as his was on earth: And then too late they may remember theſe old verſes:</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Damna fleo Rerum, ſed plus fleo Damna dierum,</l>
                  <l>Quiſquis poteſt rebus ſuccurere nemo diebus,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For loſſe of wealth partly I grieue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But for loſſe of time I grieue much more,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For many may my wants relieue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But time being loſt none can reſtore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>I remember <hi>Montague</hi> in his <hi>Eſſayes</hi> makes it a queſtion diſputable, whether the eſtate of him that is going to the <hi>Gallowes</hi> to be hanged, or hee that is a common <hi>Drunkard</hi> is more miſerable, yeelding his cenſure: that <hi>hee which is going to dye on the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, of the two is the happier (by ſo much as hee that is entring into a ſurfet, is in worſe eſtate then he that hath taken Phyſicke, a purgation for the ſame,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miſerius nihil eſt miſero, ſe non miſerante. There is nothing more wretched, then in a wretched man that Reakes not his owne miſery:</hi> and ſuch is the ſtate of the <hi>Drunkard,</hi> that he both perceiues this vice, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alloweth it in others, but neither ſeeth nor hates it in himſelfe, like ſhe in <hi>Ouid:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Video meliora proboque deteriora ſequor:
<note place="margin">Ouid Metam.</note>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I ſee the good, and giue allowance to it,</l>
                  <l>The euill is my choyce, I loue and doe it.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>For a <hi>Drunkard</hi> although hee cannot ſpeake a plaine word, will neuer yeeld himſelfe to be drunke, and after their rule a man is not accounted drunke, altheugh hee cannot ſpeake, goe, nor ſtand, nor is able to craule forth of the high way, ſo as hee can hold vp his finger, if he ſee a Cart comming vpon him. After this Rule it is a thing queſtionable whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:21300:25"/>of their conſorts, named <hi>Iohn Lawrence</hi> being at Windſor, and drunke ſo hard, that hauing a Cart and three Horſes, he was not able to ſtand to driue them out of towne, but ſome of his company helpt him vp into the Cart, thinking the horſe would bring him home. (But ſo it chanced he fell a ſleepe in the Cart) and the Horſe going in the middeſt of the Forreſt, and there ſtayed feeding, came a good fellow by, and ſtole away two of the Horſe: The Filhorſe making after his fellowes, drew the man in the Cart ſo farre that it was out of his knowledge where he was: and either by the braying of the horſe, or ſome Iut of the Cart, hee by chance awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked before hee was come to himſelfe: (which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) and he ſeeing but one Horſe in the Cart, cried out, Lord, where am I? Or who am I? If I am <hi>Iohn Lawrence,</hi> then haue I loſt a Cart and three Horſes: But if I am not <hi>Iohn Lawrence,</hi> then haue I found a Cart and one Horſe. Nor by their rule a Marchant of Briſtow (which ſhall be nameleſſe) comming to a houſe of a Gentlemans of good hoſpitalitie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two miles of Hungerford, and two of his friends with him, where they all dranke moſt free of this Gentlemans Beere, becauſe they found him liberall of his loue, in ſo much as when they came in the middeſt of a great water leading into Hungerford towne, this Marchants eyes dazeled: and hee asked his friends why they did not alight vp that great Hill: they anſwered it was water, but that could not perſwade him, but in the middeſt of the water he alighted, ſwearing he would not ride vp ſo great a Hill, and ſo waded through the reſt of the water,
<pb facs="tcp:21300:26"/>being halfe a furlong of length, &amp; of a great depth, yet by their rule hee was not drunke. Nor hee that cralled vnder all the ſignes from Holborne Bridge to Saint <hi>Giles,</hi> becauſe in a Moone-ſhine night his eyes being glazed (with the miſt of Mallego Sacke) and ſeeing the ſhaddow of the Signes vpon the ground. ſwore they were arrant knaues for ſetting the Signes ſo low, that a man could not goe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right vnder them. But letting carowſers alone with their owne definition, becauſe a <hi>Drunkard</hi> cannot be expreſſed without ſome diuiſion wee will (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee enter therevnto ſet downe a learned mans deſcription, who ſaith, <hi>A Drunkard is the annoyance of modeſtie,
<note place="margin">The di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cription of a drunkard.</note> the trouble of ciuilitie, the ſpoile of wealth, the deſtruction of Reaſon, he is one ly the Brewars agent, the Alehouſe benefactor, the Beggars companion, the Conſtables trouble, hee is his wiues woe, his Childrens ſorrow, his Neighbours ſcoffe, his owne ſhame, in ſome: hee is a tub of ſwill, a ſpirit of ſleepe,
<note place="margin">The nyne ſorts of drunkards.</note> a picture of a Beaſt, a Monſter of a man.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> But now concerning the diuiſion, there are of <hi>Drunkards</hi> nine ſorts. The firſt is Lyon drunke, which breakes glaſſe windowes, cals his Hoſteſſe Whoore, ſtrikes, fights or quarrels, with either Brother,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Friend or Father. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is Ape-drunke, who dances, capers, and leapes about the houſe, ſings and reioyces, and is wholly rauiſht into ieſts, mirth and melodie. The third is ſheepe drunke,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> who is very kinde and liberall, and ſayes, by God captaine I loue you? Goe thy wayes, thou thinkeſt not ſo often of mee, as I doe of thee, and in this ſheepiſh hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour
<pb facs="tcp:21300:26"/>giues away his Horſe, his Sword, the clothes off his backe. The fourth is Sow drunke,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> vvho vomits, ſpewes, and wallowes in the mire, like a Swine, and ſeeing the Moone ſhine, ſayes, put out the Candle lets goe to bed, lay a little more on the feete and all is well.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fiſt is Foxe drunke, who being of a dull ſpirit: vvill make no bargaine till hee hath ſharpened his wit with the eſſence of good liquor, and is then ſo craftie and politique,
<note place="margin">Aebritas prodit quodamat cer ſiue quod odir.</note> that hee deceiues any man that ſhall deale with him: of this nature are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Dutch-men, that when they drinke moſt, they bargaine beſt.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The ſixt is Maudlin drunke, who weepes, cryes, and whines, to ſee the gooſe goe barefoote.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſeuenth is Goate drunke, who is in his drinke ſo lecherous, that hee makes no difference of either time, or place, age or youth, but cryes out a Whoore, a Whoore, ten pound for a Whoore.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The eight is Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin drunke, which will bee drunke betimes in the morning, or alwayes the firſt in the company, yet will he neuer ceaſe drinking, till he hath made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe freſh againe. The ninth and laſt is Bat drunke,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> which are a ſort of <hi>Drunkards</hi> that will not openly be ſeen in ſuch actions, but as the reremowſe or Bat, delights in ſecret places and flies by night: ſo they will drinke priuately, and chiefely in the night: of this ſort may be ſome of your damask coated Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, that ſit in their ſhops both forenoone &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, &amp; looke more ſowerly on their poore neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, then if they had drunke a quart of Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar at a draught, yet at night ſneake out of their
<pb facs="tcp:21300:27"/>doores and ſlip into a Tauerne, where either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, or with ſome other that battles their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney together, they ſo plye themſelues with peny pots, (which like ſmall ſhot) goe of powring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their fat paunches, that at length they haue not an eye to ſee with all, nor a good legge to ſtand on, and on this ſort are many hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call profeſſors which abuſe ſacred Religion, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying in the day times Bibles vnder their armes, <hi>but in the night they ſlip into Alehouſe or Tauernes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore to draw toward a concluſion, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that party to bee within the predicament of Drunkenneſſe, that in any ſort through drinking doth at all enter into any of theſe precedent paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, beyond his naturall inclination: and for the more ſurer remedy of this dangerous and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinne, the beſt courſe is to auoide that which was the firſt, and is the chiefeſt occaſion thereof: <hi>(viz.)</hi> pledging and drinking one to another: which thing firſt aroſe in this Kingdome, vpon a good reaſon, becauſe men were ſo brutiſh, that at Feaſts and meetings when one was drinking his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie would take an occaſion to ſtab him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon generall meetings were auoided: vnleſſe they had in their company ſome ſure Friend to bee his pledge while he was drinking, that none ſhould hurt him: Which thing (God be thanked) needeth not to be feared by vs, in regard we haue the lawes of God to guide the vertuous, and the lawes of the Land to rule the wicked, and this thing of vrging one another was moſt carefully preuented by <hi>Aſhue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſhe</hi> at his great Feaſt made to an hundred and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<note place="margin">Heſt. 1.8.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:21300:27"/>and twentie Prouinces: wiſhing that none ſhould force other, but that they ſhould drinke in order: May not we that are Chriſtians be aſhamed to thinke that Heathens ſhould haue more care to preuent this great and capitall ſin, then our ſelues, conſidering there is no ſinne ſo vnnaturall to our bodies, ſo peſtiferous to our ſoules, more waſting to our eſtates: Wherefore (gentle Reader) God grant thee grace to auoide it, by my ſlender inſtruction: and mee power to giue example by my life and and conuerſation, and then haſt thou ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent recompence for thy reading, and my ſelfe full ſatisfaction for my writing.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>IN the Epiſtle Dedicat. reade for craue the patronage, <hi>your patronage,</hi> Ibid. for the Wine and Beere, <hi>your Wine and Beere:</hi> Ibid. for it better, <hi>had it beene better,</hi> for enioy it, <hi>haue enioyed it.</hi> In the Epiſt. to the Reader, for which thing grant, <hi>God grant.</hi> pag. B. 2. l. 22. for the body, read, <hi>your body:</hi> Ibid. for potes, <hi>putes:</hi> ib: for parat <hi>parant,</hi> lb. for foemina vina, r. <hi>foemina vina virum,</hi> ib. for caſſum, <hi>caſtum</hi> for Sodama, <hi>Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> B. 3. l. 32. for now aymes, <hi>preſently aymes,</hi> C. 1. l. 20. for requireth, <hi>requiteth,</hi> ib. l. 4. and examples <hi>of examples,</hi> ibid. l. 17. Opoplexes, <hi>Apoplexes.</hi> 26. l. for Maſter King, <hi>the King</hi> c. 4, l. 9. for it loued he, <hi>loued,</hi> ib l. 17. for meluendus, <hi>metuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus.</hi> D. lin. 28. ad ſacram, r. <hi>Ebrietas &amp;c.</hi> for ſlabbering, <hi>ſlauering,</hi> E. 4 l. 3. for Steuenton <hi>Stenenton.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
